Hello there!
This is the "Sounds American" channel.
In this video, we're going to talk about the American vowel sound /ɔɪ/,
as in the word "boy."
You can also hear this sound in words like
"oil" - "toy" - "coin" or "joy."
We'll be using special phonetic symbols — /ɔɪ/ — for this sound.
Let's start with a small test.
Take a look at these two words:
"jaw" and "joy"
Did you notice they differ by their vowel sounds?
The /ɔ/ in "jaw" and the /ɔɪ/ in "joy."
Now, watch and compare what happens when you pronounce these vowels:
Do you see a difference in how your tongue and jaw move?
When you pronounce the /ɔ/ sound,
your tongue and jaw move into one position only.
So you pronounce just one sound.
That's why the /ɔ/ is called a "monophthong,"
which means "a single sound."
However, when you pronounce the /ɔɪ/ vowel,
your tongue and jaw move from one position to another.
The /ɔɪ/ sound is called a "diphthong,"
which means that it's made by merging two single sounds into one.
That's why your jaw and tongue change their positions as you make the first sound
and then connect it to the second.
There are three diphthongs in American English,
the /ɔɪ/, the /aʊ/ and the /aɪ/,
as in the  words "boy," "bow," and "by."
We've covered the /aʊ/ and the /aɪ/ in our other videos.
As for the /ɔɪ/, let's find out how to pronounce this sound.
To make the /ɔɪ/ diphthong correctly,
focus on pronouncing two sounds
and making a smooth connection between them.
This is how you do that.
Start with making the /ɔ/ sound.
Open your mouth as wide as possible
and round your lips.
Next,
Flatten your tongue
and pull it far back to your throat.
Place it very low in your mouth.
The tip of your tongue should be touching the back of your bottom front teeth.
Next, connect the /ɔ/ to the /ɪ/ sound.
Smoothly move up your jaw
until your mouth is almost closed.
Relax your tongue and push it forward.
The first sound in a diphthong is typically longer and louder.
So, make sure that you pronounce a nice and full /ɔ/
and then connect it to the /ɪ/.
Now, let's glide from the /ɔ/ to the /ɪ/
and blend the two sounds together:
Let's talk about the most typical mistake that people make
when pronouncing the /ɔɪ/ diphthong.
Many non-native speakers reduce the /ɪ/ sound in the /ɔɪ/.
As a result, the whole sound gets distorted,
and it may lead to misunderstandings.
Compare:
Remember,
even though the /ɪ/ is more relaxed
and the shorter part of the diphthong,
you need to pronounce it completely.
Now, let's practice the /ɔɪ/ sound in some words.
This is how the practice works.
You'll see a word on the screen and hear its pronunciation.
Like this.
You'll have a few seconds to pronounce the word.
♪
Make sure you complete this part,
as this is the only way to learn to speak with an American accent.
Let's begin.
You're done!
Congratulations!
A few words about how this sound is represented in words.
There are two combinations of vowel letters
that are pronounced as the /ɔɪ/ diphthong.
First is the 'oi' combination,
as in the word "coin," or "point."
Second is the 'oy' combination,
as in "boy," or "toy."
There's a third one,
the 'aw'.
We know of only one word in which these letters are pronounced as the /ɔɪ/ sound:
lawyer.
If you find any other words, leave us a comment!
BTW, did we say that we like your comments?
Like this one:
Hassan said
"OMG, you're awesome!
This channel should have over 1 million subscribers!"
We couldn't agree more.
We'd love to get more than 1 million subscribers!
For a start :).
But we need your help with this!
Please, make sure you subscribe and share this video with your friends.
Thanks a million! ;)
Thanks for watching!
Stay tuned on our Sounds American channel!