hello there this is the sounds American
channel in this video we're going to
talk about the American our colored
vowel R as in the word car you can also
hear this sound in words like Park art
heart or far we'll be using special
phonetic symbols are for this sound
let's recap what we've learned in the
are colored vowels overview video
the r is one of the seven American are
colored vowel sounds the R is an are
colored diphthong and it's made by
merging the AA and the Ruhr sounds as
with all our colored vowel sounds the R
is often distorted by non-native
english-speakers the spelling for our
colored vows could be confusing
now let's find out how to pronounce this
are colored vowel to make the R sound
correctly focus on pronouncing two
sounds and making a smooth connection
between them this is how you do that
start with making the all sound open
your mouth as wide as possible relax
your lips
and allow them to rest in a neutral
position now let's move your tongue into
the correct position for the AA vowel
place your tongue very low in the center
of your mouth and make it flat
the tip of your tongue should be
touching the back of your bottom front
teeth
next connect the aw to the Ruhr sound
with the long gliding movement
slightly round your lips curl back the
tip of your tongue
now slightly lower the center of your
tongue and raise its back your tongue
should be tensed
now let's color the ah with the Ruhr and
blend the two sounds together our
are
let's talk about the most typical
mistakes that people make when
pronouncing the are sound number one
many non-native English speakers reduce
the Brewer sound in the are vowel this
would be fine in British English but an
American accent requires the Fuhrer to
be pronounced so if you reduce the Ruhr
your American R will be distorted and it
may lead to misunderstandings
compare
car car park park
you
number two some non-native speakers
pronounce the Ruhr in the are but they
trill it remember Americans never trill
there are colored vowel sounds
compare
cod car Pollock Park how do you avoid
trilling the tip of your tongue should
never touch the alveolar Ridge when you
pronounce the are colored sounds
remember if you want to sound like an
American don't reduce the Ruhr when
pronouncing the are colored vowels and
avoid trilling them
now let's practice the are sound in some
words
this is how we'll do it
you'll see a word on the screen and hear
its pronunciation like this alarm you'll
have a few seconds to pronounce the word
don't skip this part and try to go
through as many words as possible the
more you practice the better your
American accent will become let's begin
alarm apartment our army our article bar
bark barn car card carpet part charge
charm dark darling department farm
garbage garden
guard guitar hard hardware harmony heart
large marble parcel pardon park part
partner party scar star start tardy yard
you're done congratulations
a few words about how this sound is
represented in spelling in about 97% of
all words with this sound the R is
represented by the combination of
letters AR that's the good news the news
that's not so good is that there are
many words in which AR is pronounced as
other are colored vowels take a look how
do you know which sound of pronounce
when you see the AR combination well the
only recommendation that we can give you
right now is this stay tuned on our
sounds American channel click like if
you liked this video
by the way did we say that we like your
comments Hanna said I hope you add that
bonus track at the end of each lesson
just to get familiar with the sound when
it's used in a sentence that's a good
point how could we forget about our
bonus tracks here you go
a guard with a scar in a car
shared this video with your friends pets
and relatives don't forget to subscribe
and stay tuned on our sounds American
Channel
you